[audience] ♪ Olé, olé, olé, olé ♪
[electric guitar intro playing]
[Fito] What bothers me about documentaries
is they lack any sense of malice.
Whoever they're about always comes across
as some kind of saint.
All kindness and good manners.
That really gets on my nerves.
I need things to feel real.
I need to see the real stuff, you know?
That's it.
Of course, in life,
you gotta put on an act.
If not, you couldn't survive.
We'd be at each other's throats.
[clears throat]
[urinating]
But yeah, malice.
-["Al lado del camino" playing]
-[audience cheering]
[presenter] Ladies and gentlemen,
Fito Páez!
[crowd cheering]
[Fito] I'm 24 years old.
I was born in Rosario.
I was thrown into this world.
I don't know what goes on here.
Rosario was a bleak place in the '70s.
There was nothing there,
so we had to invent our own world.
The plan was to go to Buenos Aires
and record an album.
We were going to make a living from music.
It was amazing, dizzying.
Music gives my life meaning.
It could all go to hell.
It could all go off the rails in a second.
But while it's here, this matters.
Somebody has to do it. Luckily, that's me.
I'd go out, and there'd be
50 girls going… [screams]
There's a lot of pressure
to express yourself.
It's like a pressure cooker.
You don't even know
why you need to let it out.
The only thing I can say
for sure is that it happened to me.
It's still happening.
THE WORLD WITHIN A SONG
LONDON
[classical music playing]
[Eugenia] These ones?
Or these? They're kind of broken.
-Not these ones.
-They've got sand on them.
-Sand?
-I don't know.
But I have to read, Eugenia.
Should I take these?
-Bye.
-[Eugenia] Bye, honey. Good luck.
[Fito kisses] Mwah.
Good luck.
[Fito clears throat]
[Fito] Music is my mother.
It's where I can rest. My comfort zone.
I float. I fly. I play.
With other things, I have to think.
-[in English] Hey, my friend! Thank you.
-Thank you.
[man 1] They put the wrong…
It's a city, is it?
Or the Abbey Road studios in Abbey Road?
The… the… the studio.
[man] No. It's wrong. That's why…
What is the address?
-Is it Abbey Road Studios in Abbey Road?
-[man 2] Yeah.
[laughs]
[in Spanish] Where the Beatles recorded.
[in English] Where Beatles recorded.
[church organ playing]
[in Spanish] The Beatles invented youth.
Just think about that.
It's pure joy. Hormones. Wit…
RECORDING OF NOVELA
Intelligence. Sensitivity. Adventure.
It's where all of us wish we'd been born.
[lively keyboard melody playing]
PRODUCER
[Fito] Luckily, they were there,
because they gave us the tools
to say, "Well, this is how it is."
Please, cameraman,
focus on that fantastic graffiti.
[men laughing]
-[Fito] It's the story of our lives.
-[man] "Failure." [laughs]
Bastards.
Who put that there knowing
we'd be driving by?
[Fito] Well…
-[Coki] You create new music every day?
-Yeah.
-You're always inspired.
-[Fito] Wherever the night finds me.
The country also opens
the door to other possibilities.
It's not the same writing music
in Villa Constitución
as it is writing here in…
-[Fito] Where?
-What's this called?
-London? London.
-[Fito] London Town.
London Town.
[playing gentle melody]
[Fito] These days, just anyone says,
"Hey, I'll throw something together."
Bearings, engines… Build an oven.
Oh! [laughs]
[Fito] Music, writing, is a craft.
Its purpose is expressing
a feeling or feelings.
[gentle chamber music playing]
[Fito] And also emotional issues
from despair,
from the desire to reveal yourself.
And of course, from love.
That's all.
Let's try to have a happy ending,
even if it's just for a little while.
♪ Today the moon will embrace you ♪
Keep going.
♪ Among its rays ♪
And now.
♪ Just like… ♪
Okay. Go on.
-["Miss Understood" playing]
-♪ Just ♪
-[flute playing flourish]
-♪ Like Mom ♪
[music concludes]
[in English] I think we got it. [laughs]
-[in Spanish] Great.
-[in English] Hey, my friend.
[director] All right.
We're gonna listen. Then we come back.
[Fito, in Spanish] Nothing interests me
more than love.
There's no subject matter
that interests me more.
-[Eugenia] Thank you.
-[crowd cheers] Bravo!
Stop it, Eugenia!
[group laughing]
[Eugenia] Saturday night…
EUGENIA KOLODZIEJ'S VOICE
…was some sort of farewell night
because he was going on a trip.
"Ten years of love…
TEN-YEAR ANNIVERSARY
FITO AND EUGENIA
…fury, romance, deceit, disagreements,
pandemics, laughter, disappointments,
wine, pizzas, and pain."
[Eugenia] The tour to Mexico
and Colombia was about to start.
So, it was a bit of
a romantic farewell dinner,
because we wouldn't see each other
for a couple of months.
"Thank you for putting me
in my place every time I cross the line."
[group laughing]
"For your smile every morning,
for your love of rock,
which hardly anyone naturally has."
[Eugenia] We came back home
and we listened to music for a while.
-"I won't get better."
-[people laughing]
That's a lie.
"The only thing I could do all these years
was become more radical about my nature,
that stubbornness that came to stay."
-"That's enough."
-[group chuckles]
"I hug you so tight near the cliff
that I want us both to fall there
and keep arguing
as we fall, even after that."
"I love you."
[Eugenia] My love.
[group clapping and whistling]
[Eugenia] And around 4:30 a.m.,
I went to sleep.
He stayed up a little longer,
listening to music.
["Enciende el Amor" echoing]
[eerie distortion rises]
[wind whistling]
-[distortion fades]
-[siren wailing in distance]
[Eugenia] I woke up at noon.
And I heard… [groaning]
[groaning intensifies]
I got up,
and I headed to the bedroom.
I realized it wasn't coming from there.
When I got to the stairs,
I saw him lying on the landing.
And my heart sank.
So I started asking,
"Honey, are you okay?"
And he was awake,
but he didn't respond to my questions.
The first thing I did
was call an ambulance.
"I don't get what's going on."
"What's wrong?"
"I don't know. I found him lying there.
I don't know if he fell."
"I don't know if it's a heart attack."
It was such an uncertain
and desperate situation
that I was losing my mind.
[Fito groaning]
[Eugenia] He screamed
until 5:00 or 5:30 a.m.
Then he stopped screaming
because I saw him
with his head hanging, pale,
with dry and cracked lips.
And I thought, "He's giving up."
[Fito] The doctors said
they thought I'd been hit by a car.
They never thought
I'd fallen down the stairs.
I had 11 broken ribs.
It was a pretty brutal situation.
The pain was such…
It was so severe, so intense,
that I thought, "Well, this is it."
"Life brought me here,
or I brought myself here,
or circumstances brought me here."
"And this is what it's all about."
"Dying in a God-forsaken hospital
in a different country."
But I had never given up before.
[somber music playing]
[Fito] One of the first smells I knew
was the smell of death.
On Saturdays, my dad used
to take me to the cemetery at noon,
before lunch,
to see my mom's tombstone.
And something disturbing
would happen there, you know?
He'd kiss the photo with his hand
and then he'd ask me to do the same.
Oof…
[man] Your mom died
when you were very young.
I was eight months old.
I didn't know her, but I guess so.
The body carries
those scars, right? Forever.
My mom died because her placenta
was removed incorrectly.
So, well, it's my fault.
So I created a character
in La puta diabla,
with which, after going overboard,
I'd tell her,
"Mom, don't worry. I'm coming."
"I'll die soon."
But I started writing
a sort of image diary.
And one thing led to another
until I finished the book after two years.
[Matías] And when you wrote the book,
were you able to let go of some of it?
[Fito] No. It often happens to me.
I can explain the theory very well…
-In the work.
And then, when I go to my heart,
something else happens, man.
It's something wilder.
So, the self-righteousness, so to speak,
of the person sorting the image says,
"No, I shouldn't feel this
because it's wrong."
-[Matías] You can clarify that.
-I can do it perfectly there.
But in life, that doesn't happen to me.
♪ Your love opened a wound ♪
♪ Because everything that's good
For you is bad for you ♪
♪ Your love changed my life
Like a lightning bolt forever ♪
♪ For what was and what will be ♪
♪ What was and what will be ♪
♪ The ball on the piano
The morning we stopped singing ♪
♪ Death came one day ♪
♪ And swept everything away
It was such a gale ♪
♪ And it was a strong gale ♪
[Eugenia] Rodolf,
sleeping in short bursts,
but in a lot of pain,
told me, "From now on,
I don't want to know anything."
"I don't want the phone.
I don't want to find out anything."
Everything was postponed until October.
This Saturday, he was going to perform
at the Zócalo in Mexico City for free,
but he had to cancel this
and other performances in the capital…
[reporter] …due to an accident
where he broke five ribs.
[reporter] Remember that
Fito Páez is working on his latest album,
which will be called Novela,
and he's been working on it…
♪ In the same place
And under the same skin ♪
♪ And in the same ceremony ♪
♪ I ask you for a favor ♪
♪ Don't let me fall ♪
♪ Into the graves of glory ♪
♪ Glory ♪
[heart monitor beeping]
["La música de los sueños
de tu juventud" playing]
[Fito] After my mom died,
my dad… this is what I was told,
spent lots of time holed up in his room.
♪ The sun rises ♪
♪ And the teddy bear or your beloved
Pinocchio are no longer by your side ♪
My Grandma Belia and Aunt Pepa lived
with us at our house.
They were my mothers in the real world.
I owe them everything I am.
["La música de los sueños
de tu juventud" continues]
We lived in a neighborhood
in downtown Rosario,
at 681 Balcarce Street.
Beautiful things happened.
My dad would take the TV out to the curb
and sit on a chair,
with his hair neatly combed.
He'd put on an elegant robe, you know?
And he'd say, "Fito, bring the basin."
And he'd put his feet in there.
He felt happy.
Meanwhile, I'd play soccer
with my friends while he watched me.
And the day turned into night.
♪ You fade away in the wind ♪
♪ We float away in time ♪
-[Carlos] Good morning.
-[woman 1] Room 26?
-[Carlos] No. I can go there.
-[woman 2] Oh, no. Sorry.
-[Carlos] I can go to room 26.
-[woman 1] No.
I'll tell you something.
Mine can be fixed. Cured. Yours can't.
[Carlos laughs]
What a beautiful thing, please.
Besides, the sound
of the epode is amazing.
Well, yeah.
It's amazing.
["Raros peinados nuevos"
by Charly García playing]
This is Studio B.
We'll record the strings here.
-But this doesn't look like a studio.
-Yeah.
-Didn't you want a spacious studio?
-These are studio doors.
-You can master here.
-Oh, look.
-So you have everything close.
-I like it, Carlos.
Good.
I didn't know there was a studio
in Madrid in such bad shape.
-Did you get tired?
-It hurts.
-Of course.
-No, I didn't get tired. It hurts.
I want to see if moving the bag
wakes him up, like a cat.
How nice.
Hey, honey.
[Fito] The real test always happens
in the recovery phase,
at the very tail end.
Will I be able to sit
at the piano and move my arms freely?
Will I be able to do it?
Will I be able to move my finger again?
What if I can't?
[airplane engine roars]
[Fito] "Accidents will happen,"
my friend Costello said.
Physical pain, physical impossibility,
gives you a dose of humility.
It reminds you that you're
a tiny little thing in the universe.
[shower running]
A turn in the forever young
that one always maintains, right?
-[audience cheering]
-[Fito shouting inaudibly]
Well, no.
Not forever young, my friends.
[utensils clinking]
[Roma] What happens
to us is much less important
than we like to believe.
There isn't just one life.
There's only one life.
But within that life, you live many lives,
each a different one.
Some are better. Some are worse.
None of them make much sense.
[somber music playing]
[playing a soft melody]
[playing "Del 63"]
My finger works.
My finger works. It was numb.
I was worried that my hand wouldn't work.
Because this finger is kind of…
Because they put so many IVs in my veins
while I was at the hospital,
that they end up numbing…
Well, in this case, my finger.
And it almost reaches my wrist.
But I can still play.
I'm not saying I can play like Monk, but…
[plays a cheerful melody]
[clears throat] I don't know.
It's the first time I've sung in months.
Imagine that.
There's still a long way to go.
This needs to open up more.
So that the authentic
Rosario Indian can emerge.
[slurps]
That's what I was told I shouldn't do.
-[man] Make that noise?
-Yeah.
-At home?
Right.
[slurps loudly]
And did you make it?
Of course!
[clears throat]
And who told you that? Your grandmothers?
Or your dad?
Yeah, my dad. Everyone.
There was a way of…
You had to keep up appearances,
remain elegant, follow etiquette.
I couldn't go to a stranger's house
and eat soup like that.
Or drink tea like that.
It was vulgar.
Well,
it seems like my nature
is a bit more vulgar.
[nostalgic music playing]
[Fito] When you're raised with love,
you have half
or part of your life figured out.
If you got sick, they'd take care
of you and bundle you up.
You had food every day.
"Come on, Rodolfito."
The school smock.
The clothes, the bath.
My dad, making me listen to music.
I mean, all of that is love.
In my case,
it was a love overload.
My dad was the general director
of the municipality of Rosario.
He worked nonstop all day.
I guess he was trying
to escape everything he was feeling
after my mom's death.
[nostalgic music continues]
He was a very mystical, very crazy guy.
What I mean is he worked
in a Kafkaesque office, like The Trial,
and he'd come home and play Gershwin.
Um…
He went from the extraordinary
tango orchestras of Horacio Salgán
to Simón Díaz in Venezuela,
to the Fattoruso in Uruguay.
The effect that music has on your memory.
To this day, I hear the sound
of Herb Alpert's trumpet
and I go straight to the scene with my dad
in the living room in Rosario.
At the same time,
he's exposing me to literature
and taking me to the movies.
He took me to see 2001 in 1970
when I was 7 years old.
He made me watch The Poseidon Adventure.
[in English] I started
to believe in your promises!
That we had a chance!
What chance?
You took from me the only thing
I ever loved in the whole world.
My Linda!
[Fito, in Spanish] I'd say that in a way,
he set me on the path to freedom,
in a sense.
No, not that one.
[random piano notes playing]
[band rehearsing]
4030 REHEARSAL
Good afternoon, everyone.
[playing "Las tardes del sol,
las noches del agua"]
Euge!
Hey!
You're demanding…
Hi!
[Fito] Um…
Since I want to take care of my throat,
there won't be any instructions today.
Today we'll do the first real run-through.
Then we'll take out
our notebooks and pencils.
[energetic rock music playing]
[inaudible]
["She's Mine" playing]
♪ Today I arrived in Madrid ♪
♪ And by chance ♪
♪ By chance ♪
♪ I think of you ♪
[music stops]
You screwed up.
Turn up the keyboard
and turn down the guitar.
It's one single instruction.
Just one.
Play loud.
Loud.
With the volume you have right now.
-[man] I thought…
-It's a big difference in concept.
When I say "turn up the volume,"
you do a mechanical movement.
When I ask you to play loud,
it's a physical effort.
Intellectual and physical.
Everything else…
The other instruments
are in the right place
when you are in that place.
The beginning is… [hums]
Why do I see you moving…?
Why are you staying on a single chord?
Oh, because in that position…
I'll do it there.
Yes, of course.
-Okay.
-Let's see what you do.
[plays "She's Mine," changing the chord]
Can you see
you're changing the score, Carlos?
You can't do that.
-No.
-Because it's easier for you.
The part is… [hums melody]
You can't do that.
It's wrong. Okay?
That's the correct sheet.
-[Carlos] Okay.
-Okay.
Please, focus…
I know it's hard to focus like this,
but since asking nicely doesn't work,
I have no choice, man.
This is the final run-through.
Don't drive me nuts.
I still have to sing half a concert, man.
Come on.
Ugh!
I can't forget that, for me,
music is math and emotion.
[nostalgic saxophone music playing]
[soft piano music]
In March 1976,
I started secondary school
at Dante Alighieri, near my house.
My hormones were raging, you know?
It was an adventure.
And on March 24,
the military coup took place.
[Mentesana] We're letting
the population know
that military operations…
WRITING SLOGANS IS A CRIME
[Fito] I listened to music constantly.
And I started to study and play.
I remember the first time
I played the bombo legüero.
I realized that a lot of girls
who had never noticed me were paying
close attention and smiling.
I thought, "Wow. This could be something."
An opportunity.
Later on, García developed
and centralized it
in the extraordinary phrase,
"How to get girls."
On the one hand.
And on the other hand, music was that,
like some sort of giddiness
or connection to a world
free of roughness.
[nostalgic music]
[singing inaudibly]
It was all sensitivity.
And, "Wow, how beautiful this is."
On August 7, 1976,
I remember it like it was yesterday,
I attended my first concert.
Charly was playing
at the Fundación Astengo Auditorium.
-La Máquina de Hacer Pájaros?
-["Rock And Roll" playing]
["El anillo del capitán Beto" playing]
[Fito] The next week, Invisible
played three blocks from my house,
Luis Alberto's band.
[Fito] Luis and Charly set me free.
They freed my will
and desire to make music.
They showed me
that that's what I had to do.
Because I found happiness,
pleasure, and joy in that.
[audience cheering]
Thank you very much.
So many people, man.
I started forming my first bands.
It was a time of intense activity
in rehearsal rooms.
We experimented a lot.
We always played in the same places.
There weren't many.
But the Sala Lavardén was considered
the meeting place
for the Rosario music scene.
PROGRESSIVE BAND
In 1980, Staff won a festival
for new bands, you know?
Rubén Goldín and Juan Carlos Baglietto
were on the jury.
That's when Juan called
and asked me to join his band.
And that was like touching
a piece of heaven with your hand.
[rock music playing]
[rock music stops]
It's a nice day in Buenos Aires.
[phone ringing]
[Fabi] Hi. How's it going?
[Fito] All right.
Yesterday's run-through was good.
Demanding.
There were a lot of instructions
in the middle.
So, that burned me out
for the second album.
Today,
I won't do it.
I'll think about myself.
[vocalizing while gargling]
[Fabi plays piano notes]
Excuse me.
[jibbers]
[Fabi vocalizing]
-I'll tell you what happened to me later.
-[vocalizing]
I laugh because, in the '80s,
I used this for something else, Fabi.
-Yes, of course.
-[vocalizing]
But the good thing is
that it can have different uses.
Yeah, of course.
Forty years later. [laughs]
[vocalizing]
That's why it's honored.
Now, you blow. Before, you inhaled.
[Fabi laughs]
[audience] Olé, olé, olé, olé…
[Fito] We were presenting
Actuar para vivir with Baglietto.
And there was a buzz in the hallways.
Some sort of commotion.
And suddenly, I see Charly.
Formidable, well-dressed.
And he sat next to me.
And he asked,
"Why are you so hostile to me?"
I froze, man. I couldn't believe it.
I knelt at his feet.
Right there, I said, "Sir, I love
your music more than anything."
He hugged me,
lifted me up, and lit a joint.
We laughed.
A few days later, I got a call.
Charly wanted me in his new band.
And when I was signing the contract
in the manager's office,
at one point, the door opened,
and I heard an unreal voice.
["Fue amor" playing]
[Fito] I turned around slowly,
and there was Fabi Cantilo.
She was an angel from another planet.
She was intimidating.
I fell for her right then and there.
-["Brilliante sobre el mic" playing]
-♪ There are ♪
♪ Memories I won't erase ♪
♪ People I won't forget ♪
♪ Ooh ♪
♪ There are… ♪
How many nights you made me suffer.
♪ …scents I want to take with me ♪
♪ Silences I prefer to keep ♪
♪ Ooh, oh-oh… ♪
[Fito] And after that, the band and I
went in two taxis to Charly's apartment.
And right off the bat,
we listened to Clics modernos.
["Ojos de video tape" by
Charly García playing]
I could say my whole life was divided
into before and after that moment.
[Fito] I saw
how that machine started working.
You are playing with García
at the peak of his career.
You know? It was…
It was like being
in Goya's workshop, you know?
Or in the Beatles' studio. I mean…
I'm not exaggerating.
[Charly] The face. Hurry up.
You're running out of time, man.
-How did it go with…?
-Bad.
-It was all bad.
-[Charly] Come on. We came to play.
[speaking Italian]
-Music.
-[Charly] Right.
["Nada del mundo real" playing]
-Stop there. Stop there.
-[music stops]
[hums a melody]
It stops there.
That's what you have to do in crescendo.
Both together. You don't play there.
[man] I do the…
Okay, then join in there. Go.
["Nada del mundo real" playing]
I don't want to give too many instructions
on that part
because I'll be on the other side.
-[Carlos] Right.
-I want you to get it, basically.
This is great.
Everything you tell us is useful.
[Carlos] One, two, three.
[music continues]
The concerts start tomorrow.
This was the last rehearsal.
I need to rest, focus, and shut up.
[music stops]
You go all out with the cymbal.
It's very close to this.
Very close. The… [hums]
That's his heart opening up, man.
["Un rosarino en Budapest" playing]
Jorge Portunato was
an important man in my life
for many reasons.
He was the artistic director of EMI-Odeon.
He offered me
my first contract as a solo artist.
What more could a 21-year-old want
than to be on the Beatles's label?
You know?
So, we recorded Del 63.
It was mixed,
and it was quite well received.
Looking back, I think it was
a way of introducing myself.
Like, "Here I am."
Another afternoon, I crossed paths
with another lightning bolt in my life.
And I saw this indescribable being.
He points at me in the crowd,
looks at me, and says,
"Are you you?"
And I immediately ask, "And are you you?"
And then we hugged,
like brothers from a different life.
DUO OF THE YEAR
PÁEZ/SPINETTA
[sweet piano melody playing]
In '86, when we were recording
or about to record La la la
with Luis Alberto Spinetta,
this music came up.
My father had passed away very recently.
And it talks about the possibility
of romance after death
between my mother and my father,
there in the legions of Orion or beyond.
♪ He thought about it twice and left ♪
♪ His heart like a strawberry ♪
♪ Always the same thing with relatives ♪
♪ He left me some records in the closet ♪
♪ A silver watch and a samurai ♪
♪ Everything itemized in a file ♪
♪ And there they go ♪
♪ Part of the air ♪
♪ On their own ♪
♪ Now free ♪
Belia and Pepa would stay by themselves
in the house on Balcarce Street
taking comfort in memories
to continue the journey.
Charito and Carri are my aunt and uncle.
They'd be their guardian angels.
I'd visit them from time
to time in Rosario.
-…tomorrow, dear.
-[Eugenia] Perfect.
[Fito] Explain it.
It's okay. I need to understand
in order to organize it.
The only thing I want, Eugenia,
is to feel the desire to drink again.
[man laughs]
Which I don't feel.
Like this hot weather, right?
"Oh, this lovely heat."
Should I bring you a non-alcoholic beer
today and see what happens?
-[man] No!
-No.
Maybe tomorrow.
Tomorrow. Or Saturday would be better.
When the first stage ends.
Saturday. Are you here on Saturday?
-I'm here on Saturday.
-Saturday.
First stage, but… I told you this.
-Non-alcoholic beer, ice-cold.
-My first show.
I'll accept under these conditions.
If it's not truly ice-cold,
the way I like it…
-You know how cold I like it.
-Yes.
I'll switch to the other one.
There's no…
I'll switch immediately.
It has to have…
It has to be just as ice-cold or colder.
[Eugenia] Okay.
MOVISTAR ARENA
4030 CONCERT
[electrifying rock intro playing]
-Wait. How's that?
-It hurts like hell.
-Does it?
-Yes.
I won't see you anymore. But you're okay.
You look good. Or does it hurt?
We men have some orders to fulfill.
Does it hurt right now?
I think I'll have my first drink tonight.
-No! You…
-After two and a half months.
No.
In the other interview,
you told me you'd quit all drugs.
I was told I could drink.
Alcohol is a drug according to NA.
Well, Fabiana. I will drink.
I'm not Fabiana. [laughs]
[suspenseful music playing]
I get asked for everything.
Never one for me.
[Eugenia] One day, your face
will open and fall off.
[Fito] Why?
[Eugenia] Because, honey.
You can't say that.
-You.
-[Fito] There was never a…
One of the most demanding
and spoiled people on Earth.
-[Fito laughs]
-[Eugenia] In the galaxy.
I don't have a mom.
-[Eugenia] So what?
-People without moms get spoiled.
[nostalgic music playing]
[reporter] Your first solo LP was Del 63.
You're recording another LP
that apparently shows that openness.
-Rock and roll…
-It's the same with Giros.
[playing "Giros"]
See? Giros. It's…
There's still… The tango thing is there.
Or the phrasing of a chacarera, which is…
♪ Who said that all is lost? ♪
♪ I come to offer my heart ♪
[audience cheering]
["Yo vengo a ofrecer mi corazón" playing]
I come to offer my heart.
On December 6, 1985,
we presented Giros at Luna Park.
It was totally packed.
And it was a night of consecration.
You know? The people from Rosario.
♪ I come to offer my heart ♪
♪ So much blood the river has taken ♪
♪ It won't be easy ♪
♪ I know what happens ♪
♪ It won't be as simple as I thought ♪
♪ Like opening… ♪
♪ Your chest and letting out your soul ♪
♪ A stab of love ♪
I wrote "Yo vengo a ofrecer mi corazón"
in a couple of hours
in the dining room
of the house Fabi and I had
with a DX7, a piece of paper, and a pen.
It was one of the few songs
where lyrics and music
appeared simultaneously.
♪ When the satellites aren't enough ♪
♪ I come to offer my heart ♪
[Eugenia] I can't believe it's today.
Two months ago,
we were stuck in a hospital.
-I was screaming in pain.
-Yeah.
-That's also why I'm so excited.
-And you by my side.
Always.
[speaking indistinctly]
-Here?
-No, I'm sure it's here.
No, here…
As always, I don't want to forget
to tell you and remind you
how important you are in my life.
And in this very special moment,
someone sent me a lesson.
And I'm learning it. With you.
So, let's end the year with a party.
[all] Let's go!
[cheering]
-Let's go.
-[man] Let's go!
[Fito] This experience was very special.
These concerts.
First, because of the comeback.
To see if I could do it or not.
You don't know until you're on the stage.
And then, I was in the middle
of withdrawal syndrome.
So, I was constantly breaking down.
At the same time, I'd sing "Normal 1,"
remember my house in Rosario, and…
I couldn't sing in rehearsals sometimes.
[audience cheering]
The toxic emotional resonance,
if you will,
of the sensitivity provided by opioids,
combined with the emotional resonance
of the lyrics and the music.
And those words,
transcending time and one's life.
And the lives of all the people
who listened to it too.
It creates an overwhelming emotion.
[audience cheering]
Martín Rodríguez, my friend,
had warned me about that.
He said, "Careful.
You'll meet the kid you once were."
"Careful with what you do then."
["Ciudad de pobres corazones" playing]
♪ In this fucking city ♪
♪ Everything burns and goes away ♪
♪ Poor hearts get killed ♪
♪ Yeah! ♪
[music fades]
[volume increases]
♪ I don't want to go out for a smoke ♪
♪ I don't want to go out
On the streets with you ♪
♪ I don't want to start thinking ♪
♪ Who placed the dope in the old drawer ♪
♪ Oh! ♪
♪ Good morning, Lexotanil ♪
♪ Good morning, ma'am ♪
♪ Good morning, Doctor ♪
♪ Damn your love ♪
♪ Your immense kingdom
And your longed-for pain ♪
♪ Oh! Oh! ♪
[song fades out]
[unsettling music playing]
[Fito] I was in Rio.
That was in '86.
November 7, if I'm not mistaken.
I'd just finished playing
at the Circo Voador that evening.
Fortunato told me.
He was the president of EMI.
-He was shaking.
-[phone ringing]
[phone continues ringing]
FITO PÁEZ'S GRANDMOTHER
AND AUNT MURDERED
[somber music playing]
NO LEADS IN THE MURDER OF THE THREE WOMEN
[Fito] When it happened,
Charly was in Rio.
He didn't leave my side
for the first 48 hours, I'd say.
He took me to the beach. Stayed with me.
We didn't talk. He hugged me.
It was a very hazy period.
I was drinking, I don't know, two
or three bottles of whiskey per hour.
To ease the pain, right?
I literally went crazy.
[Charito] Fito was in bad shape.
Fito is very attached to his family.
-Look at what a house means.
-Yes.
The memories of so many years.
UNCLE AND AUNT
And it was a hard blow.
Of all the pain he suffered,
that one was terrible.
["Track Track" playing]
[Cantilo] Fito would cry at night.
I didn't know how to console him.
I'd stay by his side,
but I didn't know what to say to him.
I didn't know what to do.
♪ Time doesn't go by, at least for me… ♪
Do you like the audience?
What do you want from them?
No, I don't like the audience.
I don't like large crowds.
I couldn't stand the world.
I guess I didn't have
the courage to kill myself.
I was in deep anguish.
When you're on a balcony
with one foot out and one foot in…
I was lucky to have Fabi
telling me, "Fito, come here."
I pulled my leg back in
and went inside the apartment.
And I started making the album right away.
["Ciudad de pobres corazones" playing]
Finally, what emerges
is a powerful, undeniable riff
that imposes metropolitan violence.
♪ Everything burns and goes away ♪
I wasn't offering my heart anymore.
What for? To have it broken?
♪ Poor hearts get killed ♪
♪ Poor hearts… ♪
It was a cry of hatred.
"Motherfuckers."
♪ Poor hearts get killed ♪
♪ Yeah! ♪
There's a terrible sentence there.
I tell God, "Damn your love, your kingdom,
and your longed-for pain."
Sometimes I shake
when I think about how I repeat that line.
And on the other hand,
it's a man's strength.
He can do anything, in the sense
that he can get rid of all that.
Maybe I'll have to scream it
until the day I die.
To be able to coexist with that idea.
["Ciudad de pobres corazones" continues]
[cheering continues in the distance]
[Fito speaks indistinctly]
Ah…
Should I turn on the shower?
-No.
-No? Not yet.
-Let me relax for a bit.
-Sure, don't worry.
[melancholic piano music playing]
[tone beeps]
[Fito] Mati, I just woke up.
I spoke with Eugenia,
and we're going to separate.
I'm very fragile and vulnerable, Mati.
And intolerant, you know? That too.
I see light in the distance…
but the road ahead will be hard.
I love you.
Are you okay?
SON
MEXICO CITY
Well, 2025 is starting.
The good news is
we're going back to the Zócalo.
To the Auditorio Nacional. To Guadalajara.
We're in Mexico.
I'm so happy to start the year there.
The July Spanish tour was confirmed too,
so we're going to have a great year.
Thank goodness, right?
I had a daughter, but,
apparently, I've slipped away
into oblivion.
In a black hole.
But at least two sentences.
"Hi, Dad. How are you?"
Anyway… I love you.
At some point in 1986,
I rented a house in Caballito,
in Pasaje La Mar.
I had brought a Prince poster,
of Sign O' the Times.
It was a great laboratory.
I made Ciudad de pobres corazones there.
We rehearsed La la la.
I wrote Ey!, Novela, Tercer Mundo.
At that time, I felt I had to shake off
of the macabre tone of Ciudad.
I had to move forward
and not get bogged down.
The first nine songs were going
to be the next album, Ey!
And so Novela was shelved for years.
Things with Fabi were going downhill.
I was a bit numb to it
because I was out of my mind.
From the disco to the thing, you know?
[Fito] I wasn't helping.
I drank all day long, played the piano,
rehearsed, recorded.
[Cantilo] He'd call
the answering machine. "Fabi."
-[Fito] She was a hurricane.
-[Cantilo] Drunk.
He was already a drunk.
[Fito] And between verses and lines,
in the middle of all that,
the end of the romance was hiding.
[Cantilo] I never left.
He did.
[Fito] What comes next is
the story of a girlfriend I had
who always drove me crazy
and threw plates at me.
I wrote this song for her.
♪ She went down the alley ♪
♪ Where he was ♪
♪ Then she threw up that rum ♪
♪ Staining the wall ♪
I remember that after Ey! came out,
Roly Hernández,
in the same office
where Jorge Portunato had hired me,
fired me from the company.
He said they wouldn't renew my contract.
♪ …his life ♪
♪ But that was okay… ♪
[Fito] So yeah, it was a shitty period.
Without a penny to my name.
I was reading Bukowski, I remember.
He was a great companion.
He understood me.
My house was a graveyard
of cigarettes and beer cans.
One afternoon, my aunt and uncle,
Charito and Carrizo, rang my doorbell.
They were very alarmed by what they saw.
The whole thing was a mess.
They took me out to dinner.
I hadn't eaten in months.
And after that visit…
family came back into my life.
["You Got It" by Roy Orbison playing]
I'd go out to walk
on the street with my Discman,
listening to "You Got It" by Roy Orbison.
It made me somewhat happy
to see the sun again.
That's when Tercer Mundo took shape.
Tercer Mundo is a very rebellious album.
Ladies and gentlemen,
I live in this neighborhood.
They sell coke here.
Girls go wild.
Priests are drug dealers.
Politicians are terrible.
A boy who used to sell flowers
now has a gun.
That's how it is.
♪ They met by chance in a café ♪
♪ With tired souls from so much walking ♪
♪ She had a carnation in her hand ♪
♪ He approached her
And asked if she was okay ♪
♪ She could barely reach
The window on tiptoes ♪
♪ And he took her
For a walk down Corrientes ♪
The story of "11 y 6" is about two kids
on Corrientes Street,
an 11-year-old boy and a 6-year-old girl,
who simply fall in love in 1985.
-Five years later…
-[audience cheering]
Five years later… the government changed.
Alfonsín is gone. Menem takes over.
Violence gets much worse on the streets.
This boy is no longer 11. He's 15.
And this happens, right?
["El chico de la tapa" playing]
♪ The boy on the cover was selling flowers
On Corrientes ♪
♪ Then he lost his girl
In a room in some hospital ♪
♪ And today, kindly
And with a big smile on his face ♪
♪ He stops you on the street
If you don't give it up, he attacks you ♪
ZÓCALO
MEXICO CITY
[female vendor] Mugs, 50 pesos each!
50 pesos! Mugs, 50 pesos each!
LIVING
WITHOUT LOVE
LIVE
Sorry.
[male vendor] This is delicious!
-[woman 1] We were following you.
-[woman 2] Yeah.
-I texted your mom.
-And?
I sent her a message.
-Did she answer?
-Yes.
-And?
-I explained everything.
And she understood.
She replied quickly, within an hour.
-[Martín] Is everything okay?
-Yeah. Yeah.
[emotional music playing]
[Fito] The first time I saw Cecilia Roth
was at a movie theater in Madrid.
[woman] I want to have a party.
There'll be music, alcohol, porn, drugs…
-[man] Hard drugs.
-[woman] Only the stimulating kind.
I met him in José Ignacio,
Uruguay, a couple of years ago,
at a costume party we had planned.
And he showed up.
I remember he weighed 55 kilos
when I met him.
The first time we slept together,
I untangled his hair.
I felt like it was
an act of general untangling.
And I think he was going through
a pretty tangled-up moment.
[Fito] She absolutely dazzled me.
All of that was a source of inspiration
and a vital way
to reinsert myself into life.
[Cecilia] It was like, "I wasn't looking
for love, and I saw you," for both of us.
[Fito] That summer,
El amor después del amor was released.
[audience cheering]
[cheering and whistling]
Fito! Fito! Fito! Fito!
[audience whistling]
["El amor después del amor" playing]
♪ Maybe love after love ♪
♪ Looks like this ray of sun ♪
♪ And now that I searched ♪
♪ And now that I found ♪
♪ The perfume that pain carries ♪
♪ In the essence of souls ♪
♪ Every religion says ♪
♪ But I think it is love ♪
♪ After love ♪
[woman] ♪ Yeah! Yeah! ♪
[vocalizing]
♪ Yeah! Yeah! Yeah! ♪
♪ Ooh, ooh! ♪
[vocalizing]
[Fito] ♪ Maybe love after love ♪
♪ Looks like this ray of sun ♪
♪ And now that I searched ♪
♪ And now that I found ♪
♪ The perfume that my pain carries ♪
♪ In the essence of souls ♪
♪ Every religion says ♪
Oh, Fito Páez!
What kind of Fito are you?
Adolfito, Rodolfito, or Grafito?
-They call me Pito Fáez.
-Pito Fáez?
[reporter] Is it hard to create
after the success
of El amor después del amor?
The hard part's coming here,
not being able to take two steps.
HAVANA
CUBA
[Fito] I was always out and about.
Then I couldn't go out, go for a bite…
I couldn't do anything.
I went from the bed to the living room.
It was also fun
because it was like the Rolling Stones.
You'd go anywhere, and it was amazing.
No one is ready
for such massive popularity and success.
You're not born ready for that.
[audience] ♪ Olé, olé, olé, olé!
Fito! Fito! ♪
♪ Olé, olé, olé, olé! Fito, Fito! ♪
[Fito] What happened
in "Alegría a mi corazón"?
The last modulation.
How many times did I tell them, man?
-[man] Do you care?
-[Fito] I do, man.
I care a lot.
Will it change the course
of the universe? No.
But I work for this to go well.
And if it doesn't, it bothers me.
[phone ringing]
[Fito] Diego, can you explain to me
how the whole band
messes up the modulation at the end?
-Oh no. It was amazing.
-No, man. It ruined my night.
Give them hell, man! Give them hell.
It's what we always say about the end.
If you play the last chord wrong,
the concert is shit.
And it was.
-Yeah, yeah…
-I can't keep it in.
I'm sorry, but I can't.
No, it's okay. We just talked about it.
I had to take it.
Everyone!
No one played it, man. No one.
Me neither.
That's what I'm saying.
Go to a witch, get an exorcism.
I don't know.
Sorry, Rodolfo.
I'll take responsibility.
I'll tell the guys.
Yes. We can't move forward like this.
It's like having… You know? It's like…
We can't let this slide.
Because we were having
a wonderful concert.
Simply wonderful.
I'm being honest, and I can't keep this
to myself at the end of a tour.
-No, of course not.
-Okay.
-Hugs.
-Okay. Kisses. Bye.
-Are you okay?
-Yes. I'm tired.
[coughs] Of what?
[woman] Don't say that, Martín.
What do you mean?
"Are you tired? What are you tired of?"
Sure. Of what?
I swear I don't even have
the strength to respond to that.
[woman laughs]
A little bit of humor.
[nostalgic piano music]
[Fito] Hi, baby. Hi.
-[Cecilia] Oh, what a beautiful baby.
-Mom.
The rock music life isn't very stable.
Especially for the guy doing it,
who's making music.
Your schedule gets messed up.
It is kind of inverted
and sometimes it's not easy
to have a family that way.
-Okay. Let's park it.
-Where?
-There.
-Okay.
Let's go there.
[Martín] Let's park it there.
[continue indistinctly]
[Fito] Growing up is weird.
[melancholic music]
You're a different person every day.
What's that?
When you also think,
"Just yesterday, I was playing soccer
in Plaza San Martín with my friends."
"And now I'm playing for 80,000 people
in Mexico. How is that possible?"
Well…
the passage of time.
[serene piano music playing]
[Fito] I didn't know this would happen.
What you do know later
is that time has passed,
and you did something right.
You're 61 years old.
You raised two kids.
You did everything you did.
And that, you don't know how…
is something you see
when people give you that recognition.
And there's no one there.
You're on your own, man.
[serene, emotional music continues]
[in English] Suicidal tendencies.
[in Spanish] When those thoughts
haunt me, I let them be.
[man] Do they haunt you?
They do.
In times like these, they do haunt me.
There's something in me
that doesn't belong in this world.
[serene music continues]
All your friends are famous.
Others pay attention
to everything you say.
It's a hassle.
I mean, that's not your life.
When I couldn't do certain things,
the idea started to overwhelm me.
And the first traumatic event, I'd say,
was when I wanted
to stop after El amor después del amor
and both the label
and my manager at the time said no.
It was the only time
I was forced to make an album.
[young Fito] Look,
the plan with this album was…
I mean,
everything that happened around my work
was very explosive to the outside world.
So,
my whole daily life changed.
I can't go to the bar on the corner
to have a beer and relax,
or go out for a walk.
I can't go out at night
like I did my whole life.
So, I had to take a journey inward.
We went to record
the album in Sala Lavardén,
where I'd worked with Baglietto
in the early '80s.
We made it beautiful,
gorgeous, like a queen.
We carpeted it, removed the seats.
We set up an amazing control room.
We spent two unforgettable weeks there.
[young] What does every man do?
Go back to his home, his family.
See what happened there all these years.
See how I got here too.
I created an album about that.
How it works, from the perspective
of a guy who is now popular.
It makes for
a pretty interesting cocktail.
That's why it's called Circo Beat.
[Fito] This is a beautiful moment
because we just arrived in the States
to present and listen to Novela,
a project that started in 1988.
I'm very happy,
and I hope everything is beautiful.
I'll keep you posted.
[majestic orchestral music playing]
[woman 1, in English]
Welcome to A New York Evening
with 11-time
Latin Grammy winner Fito Páez.
[woman 2 in Spanglish]
It'll be in Spanglish. We'll switch.
[in English]
I'm a Latin-American star, you know?
[audience laughing]
[orchestral music continues]
[woman 3, in Spanish]
We're celebrating this project.
[Fito] Novela was part
of every album I made.
It was part of the time I spent
in bed, space, music.
It was a member of my family.
[music ends with a piano coda]
[reporter] Where does Fito Páez write?
[Fito] Now I'm an empty-nester
because my kids left home.
I'm separated
from my girlfriend of ten years.
So, I'm kind of back to how I was before.
I write wherever the idea hits me.
Sometimes it's in hotels,
on planes…
I need a little bit of rest.
Like having a house
and prioritizing walks, the sun,
smaller things, you know?
And cooking too.
[Gus] Tiny Desk?
I didn't know anything about it.
That format is amazing.
[Fito] Listen, Gus.
Yeah, we're doing Tiny Desk.
I'll be in Washington on the 6th, 7th…
We'll rehearse the 7th and 8th.
Filming on the 9th.
I'll keep you posted. Big hug.
[suspenseful music playing]
I don't remember how many albums I made
before Circo Beat. A lot.
Then it stopped. It stopped.
Circo Beat was '94. Abre was '99.
Between Circo Beat
and Abre, I had no ideas.
But I was still trying anyway.
Ice. Frozen.
At one point, I got scared.
I thought, "What's going on here?"
I was really worried, man.
I mean, I was obviously doing things,
but I threw everything away.
Obviously, the first few
times those crises happen
they're scary.
One day, I suddenly wrote
"Al lado del camino."
The whole thing, almost like vomiting.
As if I had opened a faucet.
As if my solar plexus opened, right?
I was in bed with Ceci.
The phone rang. André Midani asked…
[on phone] "Who do you want as producer?"
André loved joking.
I said, "Okay. Quincy Jones, Phil Ramone."
A week later, Phil calls me. He says,
[in English] "Hello, I'm Phil.
You're Fito Páez?"
[in Spanish] I nearly peed my pants.
He had produced
for Sinatra and Paul Simon.
He had done Blood on the Tracks.
And then I met someone
who was absolutely relaxed
and in control of all things music.
RECORDING / CIRCO BEAT STUDIOS
[in English] When the studio
is alive and working,
the musicians come, the fire starts.
It's incredible.
[Fito, in Spanish] I was back.
Five years later. I came back strong.
♪ I was a sad and enchanted boy ♪
♪ The Beatles, Legui rum, and wonders ♪
♪ Books, songs, and pianos ♪
♪ Movies, betrayals, and mysteries ♪
♪ My father ♪
♪ Beers, pills, mysteries, bad whiskey ♪
♪ Oil paintings, love, stages ♪
♪ Hunger, cold, crime
Money and my ten aunts ♪
♪ They made me this tangled man ♪
[Fito, in English] Yes, with two eggs.
Breakfast meat…
Yes, but I don't understand
exactly what you say.
Ah, ham! Ham, ham…
Eggs. Scrambled, yes.
Toast and coffee, yes.
Uh, brown toast.
Thank you, my dear. You're so kind.
[in Spanish] With everything
you made me go through,
if I didn't have an episode,
it's because my system works well.
But you could have one, dude.
So, you could become a dangerous person.
For work.
It'd be more toward you.
-It would be more centralized.
-I'll be shielded.
Doesn't it reassure you
that I'm taking pills?
-Not really.
-Did I take one today or not?
See what I mean?
I think I did. I think I did.
I think you're going
to be working from home.
[waiter, in English] May I pour
coffee at the moment?
-You'd like coffee?
-[Carlos] No.
-[waiter] Got it?
-We do.
[waiter] Let me take that plastic.
[phone ringing]
[Fito, in Spanish] Well, at some point,
someone was going to call me
before my Berklee lecture, right?
Yes, me. Here I am.
Yes, but I called you, Margarita.
Remind my son, Diana,
that today his father will give a lecture
at Berklee University.
And I haven't received any calls.
I didn't get any flowers.
The dollar is pricey.
Come on, Dad.
You just asked, "Who's calling me?"
-I'm calling you.
-No, Margarita. I called you.
[Margarita scoffs]
Okay, but I asked how you were doing.
"I asked how you were doing"
is the same as "I'm calling you."
-It's the same.
-Yes.
-[Martín] Congratulations.
-No, to cheer me on.
Yeah. We're with you.
[woman laughs]
You and my daughter are the worst.
You're two rascals.
This is neglect.
♪ Maldivina is blonder than Marilyn ♪
♪ Turbialuz is wearing black by Ramírez ♪
Listen, I feel neglected today.
Oh, God!
-[laughs]
-I love you. [kisses]
Love you. Bye.
[Fito] Two, three…
♪ La, la, la, la, la ♪
♪ La, le, li, le, li, le, le ♪
♪ La, li, li, le, la, la ♪
[cheering]
Um…
-It's not a rock concert today.
-[group laughs]
[in English] It's not
a rock-and-roll concert today.
It's an extract of an essay about music
in the 21st century.
[in Spanish] So,
"Music in Times of Mass Dementia."
Today, the world music seems
to be on its deathbed.
The lack of passion
in today's music is overwhelming.
This territory has been conquered
by the owners of the world
in search of
the annihilation of specificities,
shattering with the greatest amount
of force
the lightning
of musical language standardization
in all its imaginable forms."
What do you want? More money? More land?
More shares, more cars, more yachts?
What are you going to do
with all that, man?
It's simple.
You have to share, make the audience cry.
Make them sing together.
We feel good when we're all together,
because together we'll go
to an unknown place.
"Music is positive."
"It helps, accompanies,
teaches, heals, and transforms."
"Music as a weapon
against all the evils of this world."
Something I never thought I'd write,
but that I thought was appropriate
for wrapping up with,
is the "Manual for Today's Youth."
[group chuckles]
"Listen in silence
to music you're not familiar with,
for one hour,
turning off any distracting devices."
"If you don't have kids,
throw everything away, and do only this."
"Make love to the music
you like the most."
"Dance to Argentine and Colombian cumbia.
Learn to see the differences."
[students laughing]
"Dance to Prince and Babasónicos.
Learn to see the differences."
LIBRARY OF CONGRESS
WASHINGTON, D.C.
"Learn from the masters.
Masters are not just musicians."
"Anyone can teach you
something about life."
-Ah! No! No!
-[in English] Yeah. That's Mozart.
And no mistakes. No correcting. Ink.
-There's nothing.
-[Fito] It's like you're touching God. No?
If God exists, it's in Mozart.
[in Spanish] "Getting frustrated
is the best thing that can happen."
"When you find your voice,
you won't want to go back to shore."
"Just play music
and drink with your friends."
"Music has taught you this whole time
that you still have a long way to go,
and that in the time you have left
to live,
you'll be comforted by the love
of all the good and honest things
you've given to others."
[group whistles and cheers]
[upbeat music playing]
[Fito] Thank you all.
You're wonderful musicians.
Let's focus.
-This.
-I don't know if I'll go to dinner.
-[man] Rest your voice.
-[woman] No, go rest.
[suspenseful music playing]
[Fito coughs]
[continues coughing]
[reporter speaking indistinctly on news]
[reporter 1] That's right, Valentina.
There's a clear trend.
If you're Argentine
and want to go on vacation,
you'll find that most people tell us
they choose Brazil or Chile for shopping.
But people coming
from abroad to Argentina…
["139 Lexatins" playing]
I had split up with Cecilia.
Cecilia had split up
with me, to be more precise.
And I was very depressed.
-Is this Chacras de Hummus?
-Yeah.
[Fito] Coki and Carlos,
my two best friends in life.
Always by my side, you know? Nearby.
Raising my kids and making music.
We're presenting Martín's album.
His first album, called Palangana.
We made a beautiful pact once.
If any of us falls at any point,
the other two will destroy him.
[Coki] Pure Brazil.
[Fito] What are you? The rhythm duo?
And so, these two would give me
a very hard time, right?
"Oh, look.
The gentleman is depressed," they'd say.
["Volver a mí" playing]
It was a gesture of love and encouragement
because it made us laugh.
It always made us laugh.
Guys, I'm here!
Coki! I'm so glad you came.
-Why are you so late?
-We've been waiting for two days.
[Romina] I met Rodolfo one night
at a bar, around three in the morning.
[Fito] In this magical place.
[Romina] He said, "I know
what you're looking for. A smart man."
He said, "Here. That's me."
And then we kept going until, well,
we had…
They were fighting,
so he got another girlfriend.
Then he left her, and that's how it went.
DAUGHTER
I wouldn't trade the passion of my love
for my kids.
Not for music,
not for literature, nothing.
And now you think, "Fuck.
Why didn't I have them before?"
["Margarita" playing]
♪ You make me happy ♪
♪ When you wake up ♪
♪ You make the world shine ♪
♪ I want to go ♪
♪ To the moon with you ♪
♪ You make me happy ♪
♪ You make me feel fleeting ♪
♪ I want to go ♪
♪ To the moon with you ♪
♪ Ah! ♪
♪ Long live the world and life ♪
♪ Long live voices and excitement ♪
♪ This is what I want
To leave you, Margarita ♪
♪ A world that's
A bit more Rolling Stone ♪
[coughs] Coming.
Dear Roque, look.
I woke up today, first 37,
then 38.3, then 38.7.
That was the last one.
I have a high fever
half an hour before the concert.
[rehearses a cheerful melody]
[tuba melody on keyboard]
[saxophonist tuning]
[in English] Thank you.
Uh, Carlos, your acoustic guitar, please.
[in Spanish] It's four songs.
I do have some energy.
[drummer playing beat]
[Fito huffs]
Ugh…
It's burning.
-My head. A lot.
-[woman] Your head?
-We can always cancel.
-No.
-But you can…
-The day after tomorrow, yes.
Want another one now?
[emotional piano music playing]
[speaking inaudibly]
[woman clears throat]
[Fito] I'll be like Maradona
with the fatal sprain.
It could go well or it could go wrong.
I'll try to make it go well.
If it goes wrong,
you guys will be to blame.
-Of course.
-Yeah.
[man, in English] Okay, everybody.
We've had a lot of bands here,
but very few times
have we had an actual legend.
It's extremely…
It's such a big deal for us
to have a musician who defies genre,
who defies country, who defies everything.
World… known world-wide.
[in Spanish] That's Fito.
[in English] So, please,
welcome Fito Páez.
[Fito, in Spanish]
Thanks to NPR for inviting us.
And Tiny Desk
for giving us this beautiful moment.
It's live worldwide.
"Sale el sol."
Right? From Novela.
[playing "Sale el sol"]
One, two, three.
Thank you all for helping us make music.
Because music doesn't exist
without each other.
Besides, you cured my fever.
I love you.
-The sun rises!
-[woman] Come on!
[Fito] What do we need?
Well, what do we need?
I would need a lot of things.
For example, to be loved.
But you are already loved.
Well, but not in the way I want, Matías.
What do you…? In what way?
How would you like to be…?
Well, loved like the child I was.
-Oh, okay.
-But you're now 62 years old.
-How many?
-62?
No, not to me.
I feel totally like a child. Ageless.
[dramatic music]
[Fito speaks indistinctly]
[music grows chaotic]
[music peaks, fades]
[Fito] There's a photo
in which I'm barely 2 years old.
I'm sitting on the terrace
of the house on Balcarce Street.
Surrounded by toys. Dozens of them.
And yet, I'm crying.
All the women in my life and I
had to coexist with that boy
and his dead mother.
[emotional music playing]
My mom died because
her placenta was removed incorrectly.
So, well, it's my fault.
So, I created a character
with which, after going overboard,
I'd tell her,
"Mom, don't worry. I'm coming."
"I'll die soon."
So now, after the fall,
I did feel my mother's protection.
I did feel my father's
and my grandmothers' protection.
I did feel protected by the dead.
Because I didn't hurt my hip or my head.
And they said,
"You're going to stay here."
"We'll help you."
"And you'll go through physical pain."
First.
-I didn't know the other one was coming.
-Yes.
"If you feel pain, you're alive.
We don't feel pain because we're dead."
"You're alive. We're dead. Stop whining."
I'd written it in La puta diabla.
-You hadn't been able to let it go.
-Now I get it.
Oh, the artist has arrived.
Oh, my God.
DAUGHTER
Hi, Mati.
[Fito] As you get older,
you feel the need to be lighter.
Especially after the accident.
[Margarita] What's this?
[Fito] I realized I needed
to focus on the fundamental issues.
On fiercely protecting family
and real friendships.
And also on taking care
of the core of my madness.
That chaos and order
in which everything you do is managed
should be protected.
Finally, opening night.
[in English] I'm back.
["Cavalleria rusticana: Intermezzo"
playing]
[cinematic tune continues]
-[classical music continues]
-[singing inaudibly]
-[song fades]
-["El mundo cabe en una canción" playing]
WE DEDICATE THIS FILM
TO OUR BELOVED FAMILIES,
TO OUR DEAR FRIENDS,
AND TO THE GREAT ADOLFO ARISTARAIN
♪ The roses of my first love ♪
♪ My parents, the first song ♪
♪ The first kiss, the first heartache ♪
♪ The man I didn't want to be ♪
♪ The August Förster
From which I set sail ♪
♪ To distant countries ♪
♪ And something was already
There almost discovering us ♪
♪ It was already breathing by my side ♪
♪ And this is what I learned ♪
♪ And today I come to tell you ♪
♪ The world fits within a song ♪
♪ All music speaks to me ♪
♪ All things connect in my heart ♪
♪ Ah! ♪
♪ I understand you well ♪
♪ You know I understand you well ♪
♪ And even if it's all a sham ♪
♪ I know the whole world fits ♪
♪ Within a song ♪
Subtitle translation by: María C. Delgado